Finding Aid for Wilbur J. Cohen papers 1967-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilbur J. Cohen papers 1967-1987
Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.
Dean of the School of Education at the University of Michigan, 1969-1978. Earlier served in Franklin D. Roosevelt administration where he was a key figure in establishing the Social Security program and was Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare under Lyndon Johnson. Records consist of Dean's files; working files, 1978, relating to his work with the Governor's Task Force on Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions; papers relating to the Summit Conference on Inflation, 1974; and files concerning involvement with school desegregation cases in Detroit and Kalamazoo, Michigan; also photographs.
8599 Aa 2 UAm
18.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Donor No. 5612.
The records are open for research.
Wilbur Cohen was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin in 1913. Following his graduation in 1934 from the University of Wisconsin with a degree in economics, he went to Washington to work for Edwin E Witte, who was then directing President Franklin D. Roosevelt's Committee on Economic Security, which was responsible for drafting the first Social Security Act. Cohen joined the newly-formed Social Security Board in 1935 and stayed in the government for two decades, ending in 1956 when he retired as director of the Board's Division of Research and Statistics. That year, he joined the University of Michigan as a professor of public welfare administration, a position he held until 1961.
After the election of President John F. Kennedy, Cohen returned to Washington, taking the position of assistant secretary for legislation in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In 1965, he was elevated to the position of undersecretary in the department, and in 1968 was appointed to be secretary of HEW by President Lyndon Johnson.
In 1969, he returned to the University of Michigan, taking the post of dean in the School of Education. During his deanship at the University of Michigan, Cohen was appointed to chair the Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions by Governor William G. Milliken. Cohen accepted the charge in early March 1978, and proceeded to direct the members of the Task Force through the investigations of abuse to institutionalized citizens in the mental health facilities of Southeastern Michigan. It may be presumed that it was Cohen's direction which split the focus of the Task Force from the purely investigative to include research into the means of preventing future abuse. The Task Force reports are clear in their statements indicating that it is not enough for the State of Michigan to act as watchdog, there is also a need to ensure, through appropriate social programs, training, and compensation, the well-being of all Michigan residents.
Cohen retired as dean in 1978, and in 1980 he moved to Austin, Texas to take the position of Sid W. Richardson Professor of Public Affairs at the Lyndon Johnson School of Public Affairs at the University of Texas. During his career, Cohen wrote a number of books on the Social Security system and welfare policy. He served in a number of non-profit organizations, including forming and leading Save our Security, a coalition of groups opposed to the cuts in Social Security benefits proposed by President Jimmy Carter's administration. He maintained his interest in social policy and related issues up to his death on May 18, 1987 at the age of seventy three.
The Wilbur Cohen Papers provide documentation of his work as Dean of the School of Education at the University of Michigan and with the state of Michigan Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions1977-1979, as well as files on school desegregation in Detroit and Kalamazoo. The papers are organized into five series: Cohen's Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions, Public School Desegregation Files, two series of Dean of the School of Education files and Photographs.
Subjects:
Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.; Conference on Inflation (1978: Washington, D.C.); Education--Michigan.; Inflation (Finance); Michigan. Governor's Task Force on Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.; Lubin, Isador, 1896-1978
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions 1977-1979
  The collection of papers from Wilbur J. Cohen's Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions are comprised of correspondence, testimonies, drafts and reports, state departmental documents, legal briefs, and press clippings. The bulk of these documents serve to provide insight into the Task Force's investigatory processes. In addition, the inclusion of early material serves to illustrate the impetus for its formation, while later material documents its after-effect.
  The roughly chronological arrangement of the records provides a coherent history of the short-lived (March-July, 1978) Task Force. The first subseries, Pre-Task Force, contains material dating from 1977 through the early days of the Task Force. Included here are the Detroit Free Press articles concerning abuse at the Plymouth Center for Human Development. These articles set in motion the public demand for accountability in the abuse found at Plymouth. Governor Milliken's response is also found here, and his subsequent appointment of the Task Force. Other early documents are the two reports (Bishop and Davis), which offered preliminary information to the members of the Task Force.
  The second subseries contains material created or gathered by the Task Force. The series includes meeting minutes, a plethora of solicited information from sources both inside and outside the state, and documents regarding the two special panels created out of the Task Force (i.e., Special Oakdale Review Panel, and Special Panel on Care in Nursing Homes, Homes for the Aged, and Adult Foster Care Facilities). Particularly poignant are the nine folders of correspondence and testimonies, written by current and former institutionalized citizens and their family members. This series also contains the drafts and reports of the Task Force and its special panels, including responses to these documents.
  The Post-Task Force subseries contains several items postdating the Task Force's period of existence. Here are found "follow-up" documents from the Department of Mental Health and the Plymouth Center for Human Development, the draft of the "Hollister Bill", and the text of a presentation made by Wilbur J. Cohen before the Michigan Legislature. Also included is a copy of Gary Bass's PhD. dissertation (1979), for which Cohen was faculty advisor. Bass played an important role in the Task Force, particularly in his involvement with the Special Oakdale Review Panel; his dissertation contains loosely-veiled references to the findings of the Task Force.
  The Miscellaneous subseries contains an exhaustive and informative "scrapbook" of original and photocopied newspaper articles. These press clippings document events at the Oakdale Center for Developmental Disabilities, from March through June, 1978, much of which implies the effect of the Task Force's Special Panel. The two folders containing press clippings on the Plymouth Center for Human Development cover the period of February through December, 1978. These articles includes references to the staffing upheaval at Plymouth, from the director on down to the caregivers, which resulted from the investigations of the Task Force and its precursor, the Davis Panel. The series also contains 20 audiocassette tapes of Task Force meetings.
  - Pre-Task Force
    - Detroit Free Press Investigation of Plymouth Center for Human Development (Box 1)
      - Detroit Free Press Articles February 19-April 4, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Responses to Detroit Free Press Articles
        - Donald Smith, Director of Dept. of Mental Health (Box 1)
        - William Womack, Director of Plymouth Center for Human Development (Box 1)
    - Select Panel on Abuse 1977-1978
      - Select Panel on Abuse-(L. Ray) Bishop Panel (Box 1)
      - Bishop Report (Box 1)
      - Response of the Mich. Dept. of Mental Health (Box 1)
    - Plymouth Center for Human Development
      - Miscellaneous information (including accident reports) 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - Task Force Investigating Unit at Plymouth Center Report-(John Paul) Davis Report (Box 1)
      - Response to Davis Report by William Womack (Box 1)
      - Suit against Task Force Investigating Unit by Local 1837 and Council 25, AFSCME (Box 1)
    - Governor William G. Milliken
      - Special Report to the Legislature 03/09/1978 (Box 1)
      - Responses to Governor's request for information
        - Michigan Department of Corrections (Box 1)
        - Michigan Department of Education (Box 1)
        - Michigan Department of Public Health (Box 1)
        - Michigan Department of Social Services (Box 1)
  - The Task Force
    - Task Force begins-miscellaneous documents (Box 1)
    - Meetings and Public Hearings
      - Agendas and Minutes, 3/15/78-5/30/78 (Box 1)
      - Meeting of 4/17/78-Text of statement by William Womack (Box 1)
      - Public Hearing 04/20/1978
        - Testimonies (Box 1)
    - Special Panels
      - Special Oakdale Review Panel (Box 1)
      - Special Panel on Care in Nursing Homes, Homes for the Aged, and Adult Foster Care (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Testimonies
      - Offers of assistance (Box 1)
      - Correspondence regarding specific institutions
        - Clinton-Aire (Box 1)
        - Hillcrest (Box 1)
        - Oakdale (Box 1)
        - Plymouth
          - A-J (Box 1)
          - K-Z (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Testimonies
      - Miscellaneous correspondence and testimonies
        - A-J (Box 2)
        - K-Z (Box 2)
        - Forwarded from Governor's Office (Box 2)
    - Responses to Requests for Information
      - California Department of Health (Paul Smith) (Box 2)
      - Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services (Charles Kimber) (Box 2)
      - MARC-Michigan Association for Retarded Citizens (Harvey D. Zuckerberg), 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Department of Civil Service (Box 2)
      - Michigan Department of Mental Health, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Department of Mental Health, Metropolitan Regional Office (Donald K. Worden) (Box 2)
      - Michigan Department of Public Health (Box 2)
      - Michigan Department of State Police (Box 2)
      - Michigan Office of the Governor (Box 2)
      - New York, Willowbrook Review Panel, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - President's Commission on Mental Retardation (Fred Krause) (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan School of Nursing (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
        - A-J (Box 3)
        - K-Z (Box 3)
    - Task Force Questionnaire for State Employees
      - Draft (includes legal counsel) (Box 3)
      - Name lists (Box 3)
      - Responses to questionnaire (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Task Force on the Prevention and Investigation of Abuse in State Institutions
        - Interim Report
          - Draft and final? 05/04/1978 (Box 3)
          - Responses to Interim Report (Box 3)
        - Final Report
          - Notes and Draft 06/20/1978 (Box 3)
          - Final Report 07/18/1978 (Box 3)
          - Responses to Final Report (Box 3)
      - Special Oakdale Review Panel
        - Draft (Box 3)
        - Final Report (Box 3)
        - Responses to Report (Box 3)
      - Special Panel on Care in Nursing Homes, Homes for the Aged, and Adult Foster Care
        - Draft (Box 3)
        - Final Report (Box 3)
        - Responses to Report (Box 3)
  - Post-Task Force
    - Bass, Gary Douglas. "An exploratory study to evaluate the utilization of a resource exchange network in the implementation of policy to ameliorate abusive conditions at a residential institution for the developmentally disabled." PhD. Dissertation; Wilbur J. Cohen, Advisor December 18, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Cohen, Wilbur J. Text of presentation before the Michigan House and Senate September 13, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Effects of the Task Force
      - Hollister Bill, H&S 6404 (Rep. David C. Hollister) (Box 3)
      - Michigan Department of Mental Health Status Report August 30, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Plymouth Center for Human Development Status Reports May 24-September 11, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Press Clippings
      - Oakdale Center for Developmental Disabilities March-June 1978 (Box 3)
      - Plymouth Center for Human Development February-December 1978, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Audiocassetes of Task Force Meetings, 20 audiocassettes (Box 4)
- Personal/Consultation/Later Public Service
  - Reprints of articles, speeches, etc (Box 5)
  - National Commission on Unemployment Insurance Compensation 1978 (Box 5)
  - Trip to China 1976 (Box 5)
  - Trip to Korea 1984 (Box 5)
  - Topical (includes articles, consultation and board of directors files, and miscellaneous U-Michigan materials; arranged alphabetically) (Box 6)
- Public School Desegregation Files
  The Public School Desegregation Files consists primarily of reprints, reports, and unpublished speeches relating to efforts to desegregate public schools in Detroit and Kalamazoo, Michigan. The materials, which remain largely unprocessed, were received in 1990.
  - Detroit Public Schools desegregation files 1975 (Box 7)
  - Detroit Public Schools desegregation files 1975 (Box 8)
    (continued)
  - Detroit Public Schools desegregation files 1975 (Box 9)
  - Detroit Public Schools desegregation files 1975 (Box 10)
  - Kalamazoo Public School desegregation files 1979 (Box 11)
  - Kalamazoo Public School desegregation files 1979 (Box 12)
  - Kalamazoo Public School desegregation files 1979 (Box 13)
- Dean's Files 1967-1982
  Cohen's tenure as Dean of the School of Education is partially documented in two separate but related Topical Files covering the years 1969-1979 and 1967-1982. The files consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, committee files and other material.
  - Topical File 1969-1979
    - Affirmative action (Jewell Cobb case) (Box 14)
    - American Association of College for Teacher Education (Box 14)
    - American Association of Community and Junior Colleges (Box 14)
    - American School Health Association (Box 14)
    - American Society for Ecological Education (Box 14)
    - Battelle
      - General (Box 14)
      - Child development (Box 14)
      - Dierkes, Meinolf (Box 14)
    - Bell, Terrel H. (Box 14)
    - Berry, Mary F. (Box 14)
    - Blau, Peter M. (Box 14)
    - Brandeis University (Box 14)
    - Bursley, Gilbert E. (Box 14)
    - Bush Foundation (Box 14)
    - Center for Child Development and Social Policy (Box 14)
    - Center for Study and Reduction of Violence (Box 14)
    - Choue, Young Seek (Box 14)
    - City-University Day Care Project (Box 14)
    - Community School Bill (testimony) (Box 14)
    - Council on Social Work Education (Box 14)
    - Cyphert, Frederick R. (Box 14)
    - Detroit Busing Panel (Box 14)
    - Education Appropriation Bill, H.R. 5901 (Box 14)
    - Education Digest (Box 14)
    - Educational Facilities Corporation (Box 14)
    - Educational Testing Service (Box 14)
    - Egbert, Robert (Box 14)
    - Enrollment (Box 14)
    - Family Impact Seminar (Box 14)
    - Fellin, Philip A (Box 14)
    - Field, Liz (Box 14)
    - Fleming, Robben W (Box 14)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 14)
    - Foundation for Child Development (Box 14)
    - General (Box 15)
    - Goldhammer, Keith (Box 15)
    - Gorham, William (Box 15)
    - Governor's Commission on Higher Education (Box 15)
    - Graduation Requirements Commission (Box 15)
    - Graham, Richard A. (Box 15)
    - Gronvall, John A. (Box 15)
    - Halperin, Samuel (Box 15)
    - Harvard Graduate School of Education 1969-1978 (Box 15)
    - Harvard (Board of Overseers) Visiting Committee 1970-1976 (Box 15)
    - Higher Education Center (Box 15)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute (Box 15)
    - Howe, Harold, II (Box 15)
    - Imig, David G. (Box 15)
    - Institute for Social Research (Box 15)
    - Kalamazoo School Desegregation (Box 15)
    - Karsh, Norman (Box 15)
    - Kelley, Frank J. (Box 15)
    - Kembie, Eugenia (Box 15)
    - Keppel, Francis (Box 15)
    - Koff, Robert (Box 15)
    - Koob, C. Albert (Box 15)
    - Krathwohl, David R. (Box 15)
    - Kurland, Norman D. (Box 15)
    - Land Grant Colleges (Association of Colleges and Schools of Education in State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 15)
      - January-June 1974 (Box 15)
      - July-December 1974 (Box 15)
      - January-March 1975
      - April-June 1975 (Box 15)
      - July-December 1975 (Box 15)
      - 1975 (D.R. Krathwohl) (Box 16)
      - 1976 (Box 16)
      - 1977 (Box 16)
    - Lehigh University Visiting Committee (Box 16)
    - Loomis, Ralph (Box 16)
    - Merrill-Palmer Institute (Box 16)
    - Michigan State University (Box 16)
    - Morgan State University (Box 16)
    - Mott Foundation (Box 16)
    - Nova University (Box 16)
    - Pattullo, Andrew (Box 16)
    - Planning (Box 16)
    - Porter, John W. (Box 16)
    - President's Commission on School Finance (Box 16)
    - Retirement Policies for Faculty (Box 16)
    - Rhodes, Frank H.T. (Box 16)
    - School Review (Box 16)
    - Shanker, Albert (Box 16)
    - Sheppard, Harold L. (Box 16)
    - Spencer Foundation (Cleveland Conference) (Box 16)
    - Trotter, Virginia Y. (Box 16)
  - Topical File 1967-1982
    - Academy for Educational Development-Study 1969 (Box 17)
    - Affirmative Action
      - 1973 (Box 17)
      - 1974-1975 (LSA Dean Search), 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Annual Reports, SOE
      - 1969-1970 (Box 17)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 17)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 17)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 17)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 17)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 17)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 17)
      - 1980-1981 (Stark, Joan) (Box 17)
    - Appointments to Staff 1971-1972 (Box 17)
    - Black Caucus-School of Education 1971 (Box 17)
    - Black Student Enrollment in Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1971 (Box 17)
    - Budget
      - Budget Summary 1963-1968 (Box 17)
      - 1970-1971, Faculty Salaries (Box 17)
      - 1971-1972
        - Budget Reductions (Box 17)
        - Faculty Salaries (Box 17)
        - Program Priorities (Box 17)
      - 1972-1973
        - Budget Conference (Box 17)
        - Budget Request and 5 year projections (Box 17)
        - Faculty Salaries (Box 17)
        - Promotions (Box 17)
      - 1973-1974
        - Appraisal Committee (Box 17)
        - Budget Conference (Box 17)
        - Faculty Salaries (Box 17)
        - General (Box 17)
        - Salary Comparisons
          - "Big 10" Institutions (Box 17)
          - Business Administration, LSA, Education (Box 17)
          - Peer Institutions (Box 17)
          - Student Credit Hours (Box 17)
      - 1974-1975
        - Budget Conference (Box 17)
        - Budget Reductions, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - General (Box 17)
      - 1975-1976-Budget Request (Box 17)
    - City/University EPSDT Day Care Project 1978-1979, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Class Enrollments 1972-1973 (Box 17)
    - Class Notes
      - G804 1975, 1978, 1979 (Box 17)
      - G805 1979 (Box 17)
      - H613 1971 (Box 17)
      - H652 1981 (Box 17)
      - Social Policy 1978 (Box 17)
    - Community Education Development Bill 1973 (Box 17)
    - Compensatory Education (Education of all Handicapped Children Act) 1975-1976 (Box 18)
    - Competency Based Teacher Education 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Dean's Responsibilities 1972 (Box 18)
    - Detroit Schools Desegregation Case 1975 (Box 18)
    - Doctoral Review Committee 1975-1976 (Box 18)
    - Early Childhood Development and Education, Center for 1967-1974 (Box 18)
    - Education and Psychology, Combined Program in 1973-1975 (Box 18)
    - Educational Research Policy Program Proposals 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Executive Committee 1971-1973 (Box 18)
    - Faculty Promotions 1969-1970 (Box 18)
    - Finley-Carpenter Research Conference 1981-1982 (Box 18)
    - Guidance and Counseling Program 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Hampton-Michigan Program for Training Minority and Women Researchers 1980, 1 volumes (Box 18)
    - Higher Education, Center for the Study of
      - Community Colleges 1972-1973 (Box 18)
      - General 1979-1980 (Box 18)
    - Innovative Teacher Education, Task Force for 1972-1973 (Box 18)
    - Instructional Television Course 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Michigan Education Association Teacher Preparation Questionnaire 1973 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - National Study of Collective Negotiations in Education Program 1973 (Box 18)
    - New Course Proposals (Curriculum Coordinating Committee) 1973 (Box 18)
    - Personal (Box 18)
    - Service and Institutional Relations, Assistant Dean for 1970-1973 (Box 18)
    - Speeches
      - 1969 (Box 18)
      - 1977 (Box 18)
    - State Board of Education-Committee of the Whole Meeting with Deans and Directors of Teacher Education Institutions March 16, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Teacher Supply and Demand
      - 1969-1973 (Box 18)
      - 1975 (10% Reduction Proposal) (Box 18)
    - "Young Faculty in Education"-Report 1974 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous School of Education memoranda and reports (Box 18)
    - Summit Conference on Inflation,miscellaneous 1974 (Box 18)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 18)
      (unprocessed)
- Photographs
  The small Photographs series includes portraits of Wilbur Cohen, photos of Cohen with Franklin Roosevelt, Lyndon Johnson and other political figures and with Isador Lubin and others at a commemoration of the fiftieth anniversary of Social Security. (also outsize photos, UAm)
  (see also oversize folder, UAm)
  - Portraits; informal photos of WC (Box 19)
  - With Franklin Roosevelt, Lyndon Johnson, and other political dignitaries (Box 19)
  - At Anchor Award dinner and other award celebrations (Box 19)
  - Retirement Party for WJC 1978 (Box 19)
  - At miscellaneous meetings and other public functions (Box 19)
    (1 folder and 2 small boxes)
Related Material
Documentation relating to Wilbur Cohen's service in the Franklin Roosevelt and Lyndon Johnson administrations can be found in the National Archives and the Roosevelt and Johnson Presidential Libraries. The School of Education (University of Michigan) record group at the Bentley Library contains additional information on Cohen's service as dean.